<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- Created from PDF via Acrobat SaveAsXML -->
<!-- Mapping Table version: 28-February-2003 -->
<TaggedPDF-doc>
<?xpacket begin='﻿' id='W5M0MpCehiHzreSzNTczkc9d'?>
<?xpacket begin="﻿" id="W5M0MpCehiHzreSzNTczkc9d"?>
<x:xmpmeta xmlns:x="adobe:ns:meta/" x:xmptk="Adobe XMP Core 9.1-c001 79.2a0d8d9, 2023/03/14-11:19:46        ">
   <rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
      <rdf:Description rdf:about=""
            xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
            xmlns:pdf="http://ns.adobe.com/pdf/1.3/"
            xmlns:xmp="http://ns.adobe.com/xap/1.0/"
            xmlns:pdfuaid="http://www.aiim.org/pdfua/ns/id/">
         <dc:format>xml</dc:format>
         <dc:creator>
            <rdf:Seq>
               <rdf:li>Johnson, Jeff: Info Security Specialist</rdf:li>
            </rdf:Seq>
         </dc:creator>
         <dc:description>
            <rdf:Alt>
               <rdf:li xml:lang="x-default">PeaceHealth System Services</rdf:li>
            </rdf:Alt>
         </dc:description>
         <dc:title>
            <rdf:Alt>
               <rdf:li xml:lang="x-default">Application Software Security Standards Policy</rdf:li>
            </rdf:Alt>
         </dc:title>
         <pdf:Producer>Prince 12.4 (www.princexml.com)</pdf:Producer>
         <xmp:CreatorTool>PolicyStat</xmp:CreatorTool>
         <pdfuaid:part>1</pdfuaid:part>
      </rdf:Description>
   </rdf:RDF>
</x:xmpmeta>
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                                                                                                    
                           
<?xpacket end="w"?>
<?xpacket end='r'?>
<bookmark-tree>
<bookmark title="Application Software Security Standards Policy">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_150"/>
<bookmark title="SCOPE">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_151"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="PURPOSE">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_194"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="DEFINITIONS">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_196"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="POLICY">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_214"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="COMPLIANCE">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_262"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="HELP">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_264"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="RELATED MATERIAL">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_266"/>
<bookmark title="Policies &amp; Procedures:">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_267"/>
</bookmark>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="REFERENCES">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_285"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="Pre-PolicyStat APPROVALS">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_293"/>
<bookmark title="Initial Approval:">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_294"/>
</bookmark>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="All Revision Dates">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_298"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="Approval Signatures">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_300"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="Standards">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_307"/>
</bookmark>
<bookmark title="History">
<destination structID="LinkTarget_309"/>
</bookmark>
</bookmark>
</bookmark-tree>

<Document>
<P></P>

<P>Status </P>

<P>Active </P>

<P></P>

<P>PolicyStat ID </P>

<P>9023974 </P>
<Figure Alt="Logo for PeaceHealth System Services">

<ImageData src="images/Application Software Security Standards Policy-History_img_0.jpg"/>
</Figure>

<P>Origination </P>

<P>10/5/2020 </P>

<P></P>

<P>Last Approved </P>

<P>10/5/2020 </P>

<P></P>

<P>Effective </P>

<P>10/5/2020 </P>

<P></P>

<P>Next Review </P>

<P>10/5/2023 </P>

<P></P>

<P>Owner </P>

<Link>
<Link>Jeff Johnson: Info Security Specialist </Link>
</Link>

<P>Area </P>

<Link>
<Link>Information Security </Link>
</Link>

<P>Applicability </P>

<Link>
<Link>PeaceHealth Systemwide </Link>
</Link>

<P>Tags </P>

<P>
<Link>Policy </Link>
</P>

<H1 id="LinkTarget_150">Application Software Security Standards Policy </H1>

<H2 id="LinkTarget_151">SCOPE </H2>

<P>This policy applies to all PeaceHealth settings and services in the location(s) checked below: </P>

<Table>
<TR>
<TD>✓ </TD>

<TD>Ambulatory Surgery Center </TD>

<TD>✓ </TD>

<TD>PeaceHealth Medical Group </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>✓ </TD>

<TD>Cottage Grove Medical Center </TD>

<TD>✓ </TD>

<TD>Sacred Heart RiverBend </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>✓ </TD>

<TD>Ketchikan Medical Center </TD>

<TD>✓ </TD>

<TD>Sacred Heart University District </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>✓ </TD>

<TD>Ketchikan Long Term Care </TD>

<TD>✓ </TD>

<TD>Southwest Medical Center </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>✓ </TD>

<TD>Peace Harbor Medical Center </TD>

<TD>✓ </TD>

<TD>St. John Medical Center </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>✓ </TD>

<TD>Peace Island Medical Center </TD>

<TD>✓ </TD>

<TD>St. Joseph Medical Center </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>✓ </TD>

<TD>PeaceHealth Home &amp; Community </TD>

<TD>✓ </TD>

<TD>System Services Center </TD>
</TR>

<TR>
<TD>✓ </TD>

<TD>PeaceHealth Laboratories </TD>

<TD>✓ </TD>

<TD>United General Medical Center </TD>
</TR>
</Table>

<H2 id="LinkTarget_194">PURPOSE </H2>

<P>Information security standard policies identify and describe the related technical and operational security controls necessary to maintain the confidentiality, integrity, and availability of PeaceHealth's information system environment. </P>

<H2 id="LinkTarget_196">DEFINITIONS </H2>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>Caregiver: PeaceHealth employee, volunteer, trainee, and other persons whose conduct, in the performance of work for PeaceHealth, is under the direct control of PeaceHealth, regardless of whether they are paid by PeaceHealth. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>Compensating security control: An operational or technical control (i.e., safeguard or countermeasure) employed by an organization in lieu of a prescribed security control that provides equivalent or comparable protection for an information system. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>Information system: A discrete set of assets and resources organized for the collection, processing, maintenance, use, sharing, dissemination, or disposition of information. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>Production environment: The setting where information technology products and services are operational for their intended uses by authorized information system users; and are relied on for organizational daily operations. Only approved, securely configured, and tested applications, hardware, and services are deployed in this environment. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<H2 id="LinkTarget_214">POLICY </H2>

<P>PeaceHealth will actively manage the security life cycle of all in-house developed and acquired software in order to prevent, detect, and correct security weaknesses. </P>

<P>This is achieved by PeaceHealth implementing the following security controls: </P>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>1. </Lbl>

<LBody>Establish Secure Coding Practices. Establish secure coding practices appropriate to the programming language and development environment being used. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>2. </Lbl>

<LBody>Ensure that Explicit Error Checking Is Performed for All In-House Developed Software. For in-house developed software, ensure that explicit error checking is performed and documented for all input, including for size, data type, and acceptable ranges or formats. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>3. </Lbl>

<LBody>Verify that Acquired Software Is Still Supported. Verify that the version of all software acquired from outside your organization is still supported by the developer or appropriately hardened based on developer security recommendations. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>4. </Lbl>

<LBody>Only Use Up-to-Date and Trusted Third-Party Components. Only use up-to-date and trusted third-party components for the software developed by the organization. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>5. </Lbl>

<LBody>Use Only Standardized and Extensively Reviewed Encryption Algorithms. Use only standardized, currently accepted, and extensively reviewed encryption algorithms. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>6. </Lbl>

<LBody>Ensure Software Development Personnel Are Trained in Secure Coding. Ensure that all software development personnel receive training in writing secure code for their specific development environment and responsibilities. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>7. </Lbl>

<LBody>Apply Static and Dynamic Code Analyst Tools. Apply static and dynamic analysis tools to verify that secure coding practices are being adhered to for internally developed software. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>8. </Lbl>

<LBody>Establish a Process to Accept and Address Reports of Software Vulnerabilities. Establish a process to accept and address reports of software vulnerabilities, including providing a means for external entities to contact organization's security group. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>9. </Lbl>

<LBody>Separate Production and Non-Production Systems. Maintain separate environments for production and non-production systems. Developers should not have unmonitored access to production environments. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>10. </Lbl>

<LBody>Deploy Web Application Firewalls. Protect web applications by deploying web application firewalls (WAFs) that inspect all traffic flowing to the web application for common web application attacks. For applications that are not web-based, deploy specific application firewalls if such tools are available for the given application type. If the traffic is encrypted, the device should either sit behind the encryption or be capable of decrypting the traffic prior to analysis. If neither option is appropriate, deploy a host-based web application firewall. </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>11. </Lbl>

<LBody>Use Standard Hardening Configuration Templates for Databases. For applications that rely on a database, use standard hardening configuration templates. Test all systems that are part of critical business processes. </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<H2 id="LinkTarget_262">COMPLIANCE </H2>

<P>Individuals included in the scope of this policy are required to comply with the policy and all associated policies and procedures. Violations are subject to removal of access and/or corrective action, up to and including termination of employment or other business relationship with PeaceHealth. Any deviations from security policies observed in the production environment must be communicated to Information Security immediately upon discovery. If a security control exception or compensating security control is necessary, it must be submitted in accordance with the Information Security Exceptions Policy. </P>

<H2 id="LinkTarget_264">HELP </H2>

<P>Additional information may be obtained by contacting the PeaceHealth Service Desk. </P>

<H2 id="LinkTarget_266">RELATED MATERIAL </H2>

<H3 id="LinkTarget_267">Policies &amp; Procedures: </H3>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>
<Link>Information Security Exceptions Policy </Link>
</LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>
<Link>System and Services Acquisition and Development Policy </Link>
</LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>
<Link>System and Communications Protection Policy </Link>
</LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>
<Link>System and Information Integrity Policy </Link>
</LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<H2 id="LinkTarget_285">REFERENCES </H2>

<L>
<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>Center for Internet Security Controls, Version 7.1 </LBody>
</LI>

<LI>
<Lbl>• </Lbl>

<LBody>NIST Special Publication 800-53, Revision 4 </LBody>
</LI>
</L>

<H2 id="LinkTarget_293">Pre-PolicyStat APPROVALS </H2>

<H3 id="LinkTarget_294">Initial Approval: </H3>

<P>Jeff Bird, System Vice President of Information Security, approved this policy on 08/25/2020 NCPSC reviewed on 09/09/2020 </P>

<P>Formerly known as document number 900.1.439 </P>

<H2 id="LinkTarget_298">All Revision Dates </H2>
10/5/2020 
<H2 id="LinkTarget_300">Approval Signatures </H2>

<P>Step Description </P>

<P>Approver </P>

<P>Date </P>

<H2 id="LinkTarget_307">Standards </H2>

<P>No standards are associated with this document </P>

<H2 id="LinkTarget_309">History </H2>

<P>Initial import on 12/21/2020, 1:26AM EST </P>

<P>Accepted by Eubanks, Tammy: Prog Coord Policy Admin on 1/11/2021, 3:54PM EST </P>
Administrator override by Hogan, Shaina: Dir Policy Admin on 2/2/2021, 7:23PM EST 
<P>Moved from IT to Information Security </P>
Origination date changed by Eubanks, Tammy: Prog Coord Policy Admin on 5/10/2021, 4:02PM EDT 
<P>The origination date was changed to 10/5/2020 </P>
Administrator override by Eubanks, Tammy: Prog Coord Policy Admin on 5/10/2021, 4:02PM EDT 
<P>Update to links and dates </P>
Administrator override by Eubanks, Tammy: Prog Coord Policy Admin on 2/24/2022, 10:50AM EST 
<P>Changed owner from Kerrie Morin to Jeff Johnson </P>
Administrator override by Woods, Gloria: Policy Generalist on 12/9/2022, 2:23PM EST 
<P>Updated to current template: moved Definitions (and deleted obsolete PHD); added current Scope; split Related Material (relabeled subheading) and References into separate sections. </P>

<P>Draft saved by Johnson, Jeff: Info Security Specialist on 4/21/2023, 4:45PM EDT </P>
</Document>
</TaggedPDF-doc>
